These are incredible women. They never had an opportunity to go to school, they had no degrees,
Son mujeres increíbles. Nunca tuvieron la oportunidad de ir al colegio, no tenían formación,
no travel, no exposure.
ni viajaron, ni contacto alguno.
Ordinary women who did extraordinary things with the greatest of their courage, wisdom and humility. These are my teachers. For the last three decades, I've been working, staying and living in India and working with women in rural India. I was born and brought up in Mumbai. When I was in college, I met Jayaprakash Narayan, famous Gandhian leader who inspired youth to work in rural India. I went into the villages to work in rural India. I was part of land rights movement, farmers' movement and women's movement. On the same line, I ended up in a very small village, fell in love with a young, handsome, dynamic young farmer-leader who was not very educated, but he could pull the crowd. And so in the passion of youth, I married him and left Mumbai, and went to a small village which did not have running water and no toilet. Honestly, my family and friends were horrified. (Laughter) I was staying with my family, with my three children in the village, and one day, a few years later one day, a woman called Kantabai came to me. Kantabai said, "I want to open a saving account. I want to save." I asked Kantabai: "You are doing business of blacksmith. Do you have enough money to save? You are staying on the street.
Mujeres corrientes que han hecho cosas extraordinarias con su gran coraje, su sabiduría y su humildad. Estas son mis maestras. Durante las últimas tres décadas he estado trabajando y viviendo en la India, y he trabajado con mujeres de la India rural. Nací y me crié en Mumbai. Cuando estaba en la facultad, conocí a Jayaprakash Narayan, un conocido líder gandhiano que movilizó a la juventud a trabajar en la India rural. Yo fui a trabajar a los pueblos de la India rural. Apoyé el movimiento a favor de los derechos territoriales, el movimiento campesino y el movimiento feminista. En la misma línea, terminé en un pueblo muy pequeño, me enamoré de un dirigente agrícola joven, guapo y dinámico que no era muy culto, pero que era capaz de mover las masas. Y así, por la pasión de la juventud, me casé con él y abandoné Mumbai para irme a un pueblecito que no tenía agua potable ni baño. Sinceramente, mi familia y mis amigos se quedaron horrorizados. (Risas) Estaba con mi familia, con mis tres hijos en el pueblecito, y un día, unos años después una mujer que se llamaba Kantabai vino a verme. Kantabai me dijo: "Me gustaría abrir una cuenta de ahorros. Quiero ahorrar." Yo le pregunté: "Te dedicas a la herrería. ¿Tienes suficiente como para ahorrar? Vives en la calle.
Can you save?" Kantabai was insistent. She said, "I want to save because I want to buy a plastic sheet before the monsoons arrive. I want to save my family from rain." I went with Kantabai to the bank. Kantabai wanted to save 10 rupees a day -- less than 15 cents. Bank manager refused to open the account of Kantabai.
¿Puedes ahorrar?" Kantabai insistió. Me dijo: "Quiero ahorrar para comprar una sábana de plástico antes de que lleguen los monzones. Quiero proteger a mi familia de la lluvia." Fui con Kantabai al banco. Ella quería ahorrar 10 rupias al día, menos de 15 céntimos. El director del banco se negó a abrirle una cuenta a Kantabai.
He said Kantabai's amount is too small and it's not worth his time. Kantabai was not asking any loan from the bank. She was not asking any subsidy or grant from the government. What she was asking was to have a safe place
Dijo que la cantidad de Kantabai era demasiado pequeña y que estaba perdiendo su tiempo. Kantabai no le estaba pidiendo ningún préstamo al banco. No le estaba pidiendo ayuda o subvención al gobierno. Lo único que estaba pidiendo era un lugar seguro
to save her hard-earned money. And that was her right. And I went -- I said if banks are not opening the account of Kantabai, why not start the bank which will give an opportunity for women like Kantabai to save? And I applied for the banking license to Reserve Bank of India. (Applause) No, it was not an easy task. Our license was rejected -- (Laughter)
para guardar el dinero que ganaba duramente. Estaba en su derecho. Entonces me dije, si los bancos no quieren abrirle una cuenta a Kantabai, ¿por qué no abrir un banco que dé la oportunidad de ahorrar a mujeres como Kantabai? Así que le solicité la licencia bancaria al Banco de la Reserva de la India. (Aplausos) No fue tarea fácil. Nos denegaron la licencia (Risas)
on the grounds -- Reserve Bank said that we cannot issue a license to the bank whose promoting members who are nonliterate. I was terrified. I was crying. And by coming back home, I was continuously crying. I told Kantabai and other women that we couldn't get the license because our women are nonliterate. Our women said, "Stop crying. We will learn to read and write and apply again, so what?" (Applause) We started our literacy classes. Every day our women would come. They were so determined that after working the whole day, they would come to the class and learn to read and write. After five months, we applied again, but this time I didn't go alone. Fifteen women accompanied me to Reserve Bank of India. Our women told the officer of Reserve Bank, "You rejected the license because we cannot read and write. You rejected the license because we are nonliterate."
debido a que, según el Banco de la Reserva, no podían emitirle una licencia a un banco que va a fomentar a los analfabetos. Me quedé espantada. Rompí a llorar. Y en el camino de vuelta a casa, seguí llorando. Le dije a Kantabai y a otras mujeres que no pudimos conseguir la licencia porque estas mujeres eran analfabetas. Las mujeres me dijeron: "Deja de llorar. Aprenderemos a leer y a escribir y la pediremos de nuevo, ¿qué más da? (Aplausos) Empezamos nuestras clases de alfabetización. Las mujeres venían todos los días. Estaban tan decididas que después de estar trabajando todo el día, venían a clase para aprender a leer y a escribir. Después de cinco meses, volvimos a hacer la solicitud, pero esta vez no fui sola. Me acompañaron 15 mujeres al Banco de la Reserva de la India. Ellas le dijeron al directivo del banco: "Ud. rechazó darnos la licencia porque no sabíamos leer ni escribir. Nos la denegó porque éramos analfabetas."
But they said, "There were no schools when we were growing, so we are not responsible for our noneducation." And they said, "We cannot read and write, but we can count." (Laughter) (Applause) And they challenged the officer. "Then tell us to calculate the interest of any principal amount." (Laughter) "If we are unable to do it, don't give us license. Tell your officers to do it without a calculator and see who can calculate faster." (Applause) Needless to say, we got the banking license. (Laughter) (Applause) Today, more than 100,000 women are banking with us and we have more than 20 million dollars of capital. This is all women's savings, women capital, no outside investors asking for a business plan. No. It's our own rural women's savings. (Applause) I also want to say that yes, after we got the license, today Kantabai has her own house and is staying with her family in her own house for herself and her family. (Applause) When we started our banking operations, I could see that our women were not able to come to the bank because they used to lose the working day. I thought if women are not coming to the bank, bank will go to them, and we started doorstep banking. Recently, we starting digital banking. Digital banking required to remember a PIN number. Our women said, "We don't want a PIN number. That's not a good idea." And we tried to explain to them that maybe you should remember the PIN number; we will help you to remember the PIN number. They were firm. They said, "suggest something else," and they -- (Laughter) and they said, "What about thumb?" I thought that's a great idea. We'll link that digital banking with biometric, and now women use the digital financial transaction by using the thumb. And you know what they said? They said, "Anybody can steal my PIN number and take away my hard-earned money, but nobody can steal my thumb." (Applause) That reinforced the teaching which I have always learned from women: never provide poor solutions to poor people. They are smart. (Applause) A few months later,
También dijeron: "No había ningún colegio donde nos criamos, así que no somos responsables de no haber sido escolarizadas." También dijeron: "No sabemos leer ni escribir, pero sabemos contar." (Risas) (Aplausos) Incluso desafiaron al directivo: "Pregúntenos que calculemos el interés de cualquier cantidad principal." (Risas) "Y si no somos capaces de hacerlo, nos deniega la licencia. Pídale a sus empleados que lo hagan sin calculadora y a ver quién lo hace más rápido." (Aplausos) Ni que decir tiene, que conseguimos la licencia bancaria. (RIsas) (Aplausos) Hoy más de 100 000 mujeres apuestan por nosotras. Y ya tenemos un capital de más de USD 20 millones. Todo eso son los ahorros de las mujeres, el capital de las mujeres, y no de inversores externos pidiendo un plan de negocios. No. Son los ahorros de las mujeres rurales. (Aplausos) También quiero decir que sí, que tras conseguir la licencia, Kantabai ya tiene casa propia y está con su familia en su propia casa, de ella y de su familia. (Aplausos) Cuando comenzamos las operaciones bancarias, pude notar que las mujeres no podían venir al banco porque solían perder la jornada laboral. Entonces, pensé que si ellas no venían al banco, éste se acercaría a ellas, y así, se inició el banco a domicilio. Hace poco, comenzamos con la banca digital. Para ello, era necesario recordar un número PIN. Las mujeres dijeron: "No queremos un número PIN. No es buena idea." Entonces, intentamos explicarles que deberían recordar el número PIN, que nosotros les ayudaríamos a recordarlo. Se mantuvieron firmes. Nos dijeron: "Propon otra cosa." y, (Risas) y entonces, dijeron: "¿Y si usamos el pulgar? Y me pareció una idea genial. Vamos a vincular la banca digital y la biometría y así, las mujeres podrán hacer operaciones financieras digitales usando el pulgar. ¿Y saben lo que dijeron? Dijeron: "Cualquiera puede robar el número PIN y llevarse el dinero que ganamos duramente, pero nadie podrá robarnos el pulgar." (Aplausos) Eso reforzó lo que aprendí de las mujeres: No ofrezcan soluciones deficientes a la gente pobre. Son gente inteligente. (Aplausos) Unos meses después,
another woman came to the bank -- Kerabai. She mortgaged her gold and took the loan. I asked Kerabai, "Why are you mortgaging your precious jewelry and taking a loan?" Kerabai said, "Don't you realize that it's a terrible drought? There's no food or fodder for the animals.
otra mujer vino al banco, Kerabai. Hipotecó el oro que tenía y tomó un préstamo. Yo le pregunté: "¿Por qué hipotecas tus joyas para pedir un préstamo?" Kerabai dijo: "¿No te has dado cuenta de que hay una sequía terrible? No hay comida ni forraje para los animales.
No water. I'm mortgaging gold to buy food and fodder for my animals." And then she asks me, "Can I mortgage gold and get water?" I had no answer. Kerabai challenged me: "You're working in the village with women and finance, but what if one day there's no water? If you leave this village, with whom are you going to do banking?" Kerabai had a valid question,
No hay agua. Hipoteco el oro para comprar comida y pienso para mis animales." Entonces, me preguntó: "¿Puedo hipotecar el oro para conseguir agua?" No pude responderle. Kerabai me estaba desafiando: "Tú trabajas en el pueblo con las mujeres y las finanzas, pero, ¿qué pasará cuando no haya agua? Si te vas del pueblo, ¿con quién harás tus transacciones?" La pregunta de Kerabai era seria,
so in this drought, we decided to start the cattle camp in the area. It's where farmers can bring their animals to one place and get fodder and water. It didn't rain. Cattle camp was extended for 18 months. Kerabai used to move around in the cattle camp and sing the songs of encouragement. Kerabai became very popular. It rained and cattle camp was ended, but after cattle camp ended, Kerabai came to our radio -- we have community radio which has more than 100,000 listeners. She said, "I want to have a regular show on the radio." Our radio manager said, "Kerabai, you cannot read and write. How will you write the script?" You know what she replied? "I cannot read and write,
así que con esta sequía, decidimos iniciar un campamento de ganado en la zona. Es un lugar al que los granjeros pueden traer a sus animales para que tengan pienso y agua. No llovía. Así que el campamento de ganado se prorrogó unos 18 meses. Kerabai solía recorrer el campamento cantando canciones de aliento. Kerabai se hizo muy popular. Llovió y el campamento de ganado se terminó, pero después de esto, Kerabai fue a nuestra radio, la radio de la comunidad, que tiene más de 100 000 oyentes. Dijo: "Me gustaría tener un programa habitual en la radio." El director de la radio dijo: "Kerabai, no sabes leer ni escribir. ¿Cómo vas a escribir el guión?" ¿Saben lo que respondió? "No sé leer ni escribir,
but I can sing. What's the big deal?" (Laughter) And today, Kerabai is doing a regular radio program, and not only that, she's become a famous radio jockey and she has been invited by all of the radios, even from Mumbai. She gets the invitation and she does the show. (Applause) Kerabai has become a local celebrity. One day I asked Kerabai, "How did you end up singing?" She said, "Shall I tell you the real fact? When I was pregnant with my first child, I was always hungry. I did not have enough food to eat. I did not have enough money to buy food, and so to forget my hunger, I started singing." So strong and wise, no? I always think that our women overcome so many obstacles -- cultural, social, financial -- and they find out their ways. I would like to share another story: Sunita Kamble. She has taken a course in a business school, and she has become a veterinary doctor. She's Dalit; she comes from an untouchable caste, but she does artificial insemination in goats. It is a very male-dominated profession and it is all the more difficult for Sunita because Sunita comes from an untouchable caste. But she worked very hard. She did successful goat deliveries in the region and she became a famous goat doctor. Recently, she got a national award. I went to Sunita's house to celebrate -- to congratulate her. When I entered the village, I saw a big cutout of Sunita. Sunita was smiling on that picture. I was really surprised to see an untouchable, coming from the village, having a big cutout at the entrance of the village. When I went to her house, I was even more amazed because upper caste leaders -- men -- were sitting in the house, in her house, and having chai and water,
pero sé cantar. ¿Cuál es el problema?" (Risas) Y hoy Kerabai tiene su programa habitual en la radio y no solo eso, sino que se ha convertido en locutora de radio y la han invitado todas las emisoras de radio, incluso las de Mumbai. La invitan y ella hace el programa. (Aplausos) Kerabai se ha convertido en una celebridad local. Un día le pregunté: "¿Cómo te hiciste cantante?" Ella me dijo: "¿Quieres que te diga la verdad? Cundo estaba embarazada de mi primer hijo, siempre tenía hambre, pero no tenía suficiente para comer. Me hacía falta dinero para comprar, así que para olvidarme del hambre, empecé a cantar." Que fuerte y sabia, ¿verdad? Siempre pienso que nuestras mujeres superan muchos obstáculos, culturales, sociales, financieros, y siempre encuentran el buen camino. Me gustaría compartir otra historia: Sunita Kamble. Ella hizo un curso en una escuela de comercio y ahora es veterinaria. Ella es una dalit, procede de una de las castas intocables, pero se dedica a la inseminación artificial en las cabras. Es una profesión dominada por hombres y para Sunita, es sumamente difícil porque ella procede de una casta intocable. Pero ha trabajado muy duro. Ha llevado a cabo con éxito partos de cabras en la zona y es una conocida doctora de cabras. Hace poco, ganó un premio nacional. Yo fui a su casa a celebrarlo, a darle la enhorabuena. Cuando llegué al pueblo, vi un póster enorme de Sunita. Ella sonreía en esa foto. Me sorprendió mucho ver a una intocable del pueblo con un póster enorme en la entrada del éste. Cuando fui a su casa, me sorprendí aún más porque los líderes de las castas superiores, los hombres, estaban sentados en la casa, en su casa, tomando masala chai y agua,
which is very rare in India. Upper caste leaders do not go to an untouchable's house and have chai or water. And they were requesting her to come and address the gathering of the village. Sunita broke centuries-old caste conditioning in India. (Applause) Let me come to what the younger generations do. As I'm standing here -- I'm so proud as I stand here, from Mhaswad to Vancouver. Back home, Sarita Bhise -- she's not even 16 years old. She's preparing herself -- she's a part of our sports program, Champions' program. She's preparing herself to represent India in field hockey. And you know where she's going? She's going to represent in 2020 Olympics, Tokyo. (Applause)
lo que resulta muy raro en la India. Estos líderes nunca van a casa de un intocable ni toman masala chai, ni agua. Pero le estaban pidiendo a Sunita que asistiera y expusiera sus ideas en la reunión del pueblo. Sunita había roto así condiciones de casta con siglos de antigüedad. (Aplauso) Déjenme abordar la labor de las nuevas generaciones. Estar ante Uds., me enorgullece encontrarme aquí, desde Mhaswad hasta Vancouver. De nuevo en mi tierra, Sarita Bhise, ni siquiera tiene 16 años. Se está preparando, forma parte de nuestro programa de deportes, el programa de campeones, se está preparando para representar a la India en hockey sobre césped. ¿Y saben a dónde irá? Nos representará en los Juegos Olímpicos de Tokyo del 2020. (Aplausos)
Sarita comes from a very poor shepherd community. I am just -- I couldn't be more proud of her. There are millions of women like Sarita, Kerabai, Sunita, who can be around you also. They can be all over the world, but at first glance you may think that they do not have anything to say, they do not have anything to share. You would be so wrong. I am so lucky that I'm working with these women. They are sharing their stories with me, they are sharing their wisdom with me, and I'm just lucky to be with them. 20 years before -- and I'm so proud -- we went to Reserve Bank of India and we set up the first rural women's bank. Today they are pushing me to go to National Stock Exchange to set up the first fund dedicated to micro rural women entrepreneurs. They are pushing me to set up the first small finance women's bank in the world. And as one of them said, "My courage is my capital." And I say here, their courage is my capital. And if you want, it can be yours also. Thank you. (Applause)
Sarita procede de una comunidad de pastores muy pobre. Estoy, no puedo estar más orgullosa de ella. Hay millones de mujeres como Sarita, Kerabai y Sunita que también pueden estar alrededor de Uds. Se encuentran en cualquier parte del mundo, pero a primera vista, puede que Uds. crean que no tienen nada que decir o que no tienen nada que ofrecer. Pues están muy equivocados. Soy muy afortunada de trabajar con estas mujeres. Ellas comparten sus historias conmigo, comparten su sabiduría conmigo y yo tengo mucha suerte de estar con ellas. 20 años atrás, estoy tan orgullosa, fuimos al Banco de la Reserva de la India y comenzamos el primer banco de mujeres rurales. A día de hoy, me presionan para que vaya a la Bolsa Nacional de Valores para establecer el primer fondo destinado a microempresas de las mujeres rurales. Me están presionando para que abra el primer banco de financiación de mujeres de todo el mundo. Como dijo una de ellas: "Mi coraje es mi capital." Y yo digo que su coraje es mi capital. Y si Uds. quieren, también puede ser suyo. Gracias. (Aplauso)